

RESEARCH SCIENTIST, TOYOTA CENTRAL R&D LABS., INC.

Koraku Mori Bldg 10F, Koraku 1-4-14, Bunkyo, Tokyo, 1120004, Japan.

🗷 keisuke.otaki.jp@gmail.com | 🎢 https://researchmap.jp/cocomoff/?lang=english | 🖸 cocomoff | 🛅 cocomoff | 💆 @cocomoff

Summary _

Keisuke Otaki received the B.E. degree in Engineering (Computer Science) in 2011 from Kyoto University, Japan. He also received his Ph.D. degree in Informatics from Kyoto University in 2016. He was a visiting doctor course student at the University of Bonn and Fraunhofer IAIS from 2013 to 2014 during his Ph.D. course. He was also an research fellow of JSPS from 2014 to 2016. He then joined the current position.

Statements on Recent Work: I'm working at Toyota Central R&D Labs., Inc. in Japan (whose headquater is located in Aichi, and its branch office is in Tokyo). Recent targeting international conferences of our team: AAAI, IJCAI, ITSC, AAMAS, ICAPS, etc. My recent research topics are

- combinatorial optimization (both problem modeling and solving with various solvers like LP/MIP/CSP/Annealing) for applications such as path-planning, vehicle operations, ride-sharing, multi-agent path-findings, etc.,
- interactive combinatorial optimization for various transportation/MaaS applications on the viewpoint of Human-Al cooperation and/or human-computer interaction, and
- learning-based optimization framework (e.g., decision-focused learning, learning models, etc.)

Note: TCRDL is a research institute in the Toyota group, whose mission statement is doing advanced researches and development for the modern and sustainable transportation system. We often do collaborative research with other companies in the Toyota group (e.g., Toyota Motor Corp., Denso, etc.) and also with other universities or institutes.

Education

Graduate School of Informatics, Kyoto University

Kyoto, Japan

Ph.D in Informatics, and M.S. in Informatics

Apr. 2011 - Mar. 2016

- Ph.D Thesis: Algorithmic Approaches to Pattern Mining from Structured Data
- Supervisor: Akihiro Yamamoto, Committee: Akutsu Tatsuya, Kashima Hisashi

Faculty of Engineering, Kyoto University

Kyoto, Japan

B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Mar. 2011 - Apr. 2009

National Institute of Technology, Fukui College

Fukui, Japan

QUASI-UNDERGRADUATE COURSE OF ENGINEERING

Mar. 2009 - Apr. 2004

Research Experiences

Toyota Central R&D Labs., Inc.

Aichi and Tokyo, Japan

RESEARCHER

April 2016 - present

• Working as a researcher since January 2017 to present in several departments/groups.

Japan Society for the Promotion of Science

Kyoto, Japan

RESEARCH FELLOW (DC2)

Apr. 2014 - Mar. 2016

- Project: Studies on mining from structured data and their visualization
- Supervisor: Dr. Akihiro Yamamoto
- Research topics: Pattern mining, Visualization, Graph-structured data

Fraunhofer IAIS and University of Bonn

Sankt Augstin, Germany

VISITOR (VISITING STUDENT)

TING STUDENT)

Mar. 2013 - Feb. 2014

- Project: Studies on mining algorithms from structured data and methods for preserving privacy, particularly for graph-structured data
- Supervisor: Dr. Tamás Horváth
- Research topics: Mining algorithms, Graph pattern mining, Probabilistic algorithms

Projects at TCRDL

Optimization System and Decision-Focused Learning

Bunkyo, Tokyo

APPLIED MATHEMATICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

Jan. 2022 - present

• Worked as AI/ML/DS researchers, see our AAAI2022 papers.

On-demand Transportation Systems

Bunkyo, Tokyo

MULTI-AGENT SYSTEM PROGRAM, SOCIAL-SCIENCE RESEARCH DOMAIN

Oct. 2020 - Dec. 2021

- · Details are hidden due to confidentiality reasons.
- Keywords: Combinatorial optimization, routing problems, on-demand transportation systems

Optimization for Social Transportation System

Bunkyo, Tokyo

MULTI-AGENT SYSTEM PROGRAM, SOCIAL-SCIENCE RESEARCH DOMAIN

Jan. 2020 - Sept. 2020

 Worked on cooperative transportation systems and did research on ride-sharing and optimization problems, see our SoCS2020, PRIMA2020, and ITSC2021 papers.

Combinatorial Optimization for Intelligent Transportation Systems

Bunkyo, Tokyo

MULTI-AGENT SYSTEM PROGRAM, DATA-ANALYTICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

Apr. 2019 - Dec. 2019

- · Worked on cooperative transportation systems and did research on multi-agent systems (MAS), see our ITSC2019 and ICTAI2019 papers.
- Did large-scale numerical experiments of combinatorial optimizations for multiple vehicles.
- Developed optimization methods using data structures for MAS.

Learning and Optimization for Intelligent Transportation Systems

Nagakute, Aichi

MULTI-AGENT SYSTEM PROGRAM, DATA-ANALYTICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

- Feb. 2018 Mar. 2019
- Learned foundations on mathematical programmings and implementations by Gurobi, see our AAMAS2019 paper.
- Modeled and did experiments on recent transportation systems such as ride-sharing, transfer, vehicle routing, etc.
- Proposed a new mathematical model for heterogeneous vehicles.

Reinforcement Learning for Transportation System and Maintenance Systems

Nagakute, Aichi

INTELLIGENT SYSTEM CONTROL PROGRAM, DATA-ANALYTICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

Oct. 2017 - Jan. 2018

- Surveyed and tested the maintenance domain for RL.
- Worked on the warm-up problem of RL, particularly on the routing domain.

Reinforcement Learning for Transportation System

Nagakute, Aichi

DATA SCIENCE PROGRAM, DATA-ANALYTICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

Apr. 2017 - Sep. 2017

- · Learned fundamental concepts on Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Deep RL (DRL) via OpenAl gym.
- · Worked on proposed RL applications for transportation systems, including routing and traffic signal control.

Learning and Inference System

Nagakute, Aichi

LEARNING AND INFERENCE PROGRAM, DATA-ANALYTICS RESEARCH DOMAIN

Feb. 2017 - Mar. 2017

Surveyed Topological Data Analysis (TDA) and program developments for computing persistent diagrams for 3D protein structures.

Selected Publications

These are selected papers. See my researchmap page for details.

High Density Automated Valet Parking Via Multi-Agent Path Finding A. Okoso, K. Otaki, S. Koide, T. Nishi	IEEE ITSC2022 Oct. 2022
Planning with Explanations for Finding Desired Meeting Points on Graphs K. Otaki	AAAI2022 Feb. 2022
Partial Wasserstein Covering K. Kawano, S. Koide, K. Otaki	AAAI2022 Feb. 2022
Network-Flow-Problem-Based Approach to Multi-Agent Path Finding for Connected Autonomous Vehicles A. Okoso, B. Okumura, K. Otaki, T. Nishi	IEEE ITSC2021 Nov. 2021
Multi-Agent Path Finding with Destination Choice A. Okoso, K. Otaki, T. Nishi	PRIMA2020 Oct. 2020
Distance-based Heuristic Solvers for Cooperative Path Planning with Heterogeneous Agents K. Otaki, S. Koide, A. Okoso, T. Nishi	PRIMA2020 Oct. 2020
Cooperative Path Planning for Heterogeneous Agents (Extended Abstract) K. Otaki, S. Koide, A. Okoso, T. Nishi	SoCS2020 May 2020
Multi-agent Path Planning with Heterogeneous Cooperation K. Otaki, S. Koide, K. Hayakawa, A. Okoso, T. Nishi	IEEE ICTAI2019 Nov. 2019
Multi-Agent Path Finding with Priority for Cooperative Automated Valet Parking A. Okoso, K. Отакі, Т. Nishi	IEEE ITSC2019 Oct. 2019
NERO: Hierarchical-approximated Rebalancing Optimization for Mobility on Demand T. Nishi, S. Koide, K. Otaki, A. Okoso arXiv:1906.10835, 2019	arXiv 2019
Cooperative Routing with Heterogeneous Vehicles K. Otaki, S. Koide, A. Okoso, T. Nishi	AAMAS2019 May. 2019
Traffic Signal Control Based on Reinforcement Learning with Graph Convolutional Neural Nets T. Nishi, K. Otaki, K. Hayakawa, T. Yoshimura	IEEE ITSC2018 Nov. 2018
Learning Concepts and Their Unions from Positive Data with Refinement Operators	Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence
S. Ouchi, T. Okayama, K. Otaki, R. Yoshinaka, A. Yamamoto DOI:10.1007/s10472-015-9458-6. Periodic Pattern Mining with Periodical Co-occurrences of Symbols K. Otaki, A. Yamamoto	2017 IPSJ TOM 2016
vol.9(1), pp.33-42, 2016. Periodical Skeletonization for Partially Periodic Pattern Mining K. Отакі, А. Yамамото	DS2015 Oct. 2015

Awards

2020 IPSJ Transaction Award, IPSJ, Japan 2020 **Best Paper Nominate**, PRIMA2020 2019 Poster Award, JAWS2019 Hiroshima, Japan 2016 IPSJ Yamashita SIG Research Award, IPSJ Japan 2015 Best Presentation Award, IPSJ SIG-MPS #105 Kitami, Japan

Kyoto, Japan

Kyoto, Japan

Mar. 2014

Extracurricular Activity

Machine Learning Summer School 2015

THE WEB MASTER, A LOCALIZER, AND A LOCAL ARRANGEMENT MEMBER - Sep. 2015

Trends in Machine Learning, A Workshop at Kyoto University

A MEMBER OF THE ORGANIZATION TEAM

Machine Learning Summer School 2012

Kyoto, Japan THE WEB MASTER AND A LOCAL ARRANGEMENT MEMBER - Sep. 2012

The Kyoto School Project Kyoto, Japan A WEB DEVELOPER 2011-2012

• Arranged and created electrical archive Web pages for famous philosophers worked in Kyoto University